<?xml version="1.0"?>
<HelpFile createdAt="2005-02-11" createdBy="graebe" id="HelpFile">
<title>
The GeoProver Package for Mechanized (Plane) Geometry Theorem Proving
</title>
<version>1.3a</version>
<date>Jan 18, 2003</date>

<author>Hans-Gert Graebe</author>
<address>
Univ. Leipzig, Institut f. Informatik, D - 04109 Leipzig, Germany
</address>
<url>http://www.informatik.uni-leipzig.de/~graebe</url>
<email>graebe@informatik.uni-leipzig.de</email>

<keywords>geometry theorem proving</keywords>

<Introduction> <p>The <b>GeoProver</b> is a small package for
mechanized (plane) geometry manipulations with non degeneracy
tracing, available for different CAS platforms (Maple, MuPAD,
Mathematica, and Reduce).</p>

<p>It provides the casual user with a couple of procedures that
allow him/her to mechanize his/her own geometry proofs. Version
1.1 grew out from a course of lectures for students of computer
science on this topic held by the author at the Univ. of Leipzig
in fall 1996 and was updated after a similar lecture in spring
1998.  </p>

<p>The (completely revised) version 1.2, finished in March 2002,
was set up as a generic software project to manage the code for
different platforms in a unified way. There is a close relationship
to the SymbolicData project (see 
<url>http://www.symbolicdata.org</url>).</p>

<p>For examples we refer to the test file, but also to the
SymbolicData GEO collection. It contains many (generic) proof
schemes of geometry theorems, mainly from Chou's book. These proof
schemes can be translated to the GeoProver syntax for different
platforms with SymbolicData tools.</p>

<p>For version 1.3 the syntax definition (the <b>GeoCode</b>) was
separated from the GeoProver implementation. The latter is an
implementation of the GeoCode standard using the coordinate
method. </p>

<p>Note that function names change with different versions of the
GeoCode standard. GeoProver 1.3 implements the GeoCode standard
1.3. </p>

<p>Please send comments, bug reports, hints, wishes, criticisms
etc. to the author.</p> 
</Introduction>

<Bibliography>
<p>If you have used the GeoProver in the preparation of a publication,
please cite it in the following format (in particular, refer
explicitely to the used version): </p>
<pre>
\bibitem{GeoProver}
H.-G. Gr\"abe.
\newblock {\sc GeoProver} -- {A Small Package for Mechanized Plane Geometry
  Theorem Proving}, 1998 -- 2003.
\newblock {With versions for Reduce, Maple, MuPAD and Mathematica.}\\ See
  \url{http://www.informatik.uni-leipzig.de/~compalg/software}.
</pre>

<p>If you are using BibTeX, you can use the following BibTeX entry</p>  
<pre>
@Misc{GeoProver,
  author =       {Gr\"abe, H.-G.},
  title =        {{\sc GeoProver} -- {A Small Package for
                  Mechanized Plane Geometry Theorem Proving}},
  year =         {1998 -- 2003},
  note =         {{With versions for Reduce, Maple, MuPAD and
                  Mathematica.}\\  See
                  \url{http://www.informatik.uni-leipzig.de/~compalg/software}
                  },
}
</pre>
</Bibliography>

<Acknowledgements> 

<p>Malte Witte translated the code of version 1.1 from Reduce to
Maple, MuPAD, and Mathematica and compiled many examples for the
SymbolicData GEO proof scheme collection, mainly from Chou's
book.</p>

<p>Benjamin Friedrich collected examples and solutions with
geometric background from IMO contests.</p>
</Acknowledgements>

<BasicDataTypes>
<p>Basic data types are <b>Points</b>, <b>Lines</b>, and
<b>Circles</b>.</p>
  
<p>A point <code>A:=Point(a,b)</code> represents a point with
coordinates <math>(a1,a2)</math>. </p>

<p>A line <code>l:=Line(a,b,c)</code> represents the line
<math>{ (x,y) : a*x+b*y+c=0 }</math>. </p>

<p>A circle <code>c:=Circle(c1,c2,c3,c4)</code> represents the
circle <math>{ (x,y) : c1*(x^2+y^2)+c2*x+c3*y+c4=0 }</math>. </p> 
</BasicDataTypes>
</HelpFile>
